The two most likely largest inventions
الاختراعان الاكثر احتمالا انهما اكبر اثنان
of our generation
في جيلنا
are the Internet and the mobile phone.
هما الانترنت و الهاتف النقال
They've changed the world.
فقد غيرا العالم
However, largely to our surprise,
ومع ذلك، إلى حد كبير ادهشنا،
they also turned out to be the perfect tools
أنها تحولت أيضا إلى أن تكون أدوات مثالية
for the surveillance state.
لمراقبه الدولة
It turned out that the capability
اتضح أن القدرة
to collect data, information and connections
على جمع البيانات والمعلومات والاتصالات
about basically any of us and all of us
عن ابتداء اي منا و كلنا
is exactly what we've been hearing
هو بالضبط ما منا نسمع عنه
throughout of the summer through revelations and leaks
طوال فصل الصيف من خلال الكشف و التسريبات
about Western intelligence agencies,
عن وكالات الاستخبارات الغربية
mostly U.S. intelligence agencies,
في الغالب وكالات المخابرات الامريكية،
watching over the rest of the world.
تتفرج على بقية العالم.
We've heard about these starting with the
لقد سمعنا عن هذا ابتداء ب
revelations from June 6.
الكشف في الفترة من 6 يونيو حزيران.
Edward Snowden started leaking information,
بدأ إدوارد سنودن تسريب المعلومات،
top secret classified information,
معلومات في غاية السرية،
from the U.S. intelligence agencies,
من وكالات المخابرات الامريكية،
and we started learning about things like PRISM
ثم بدائنا المعرفة عن اشياء مثل ال " برزم "
and XKeyscore and others.
و ال " اكس كي سكور " و غيرها
And these are examples of the kinds of programs
و هذه امثلة لانواع البرامج
U.S. intelligence agencies are running right now,
التي تديرها الوكالات الاستخبارية الامريكية
against the whole rest of the world.
على جميع انحاء العالم
And if you look back about the forecasts
وإذا نظرت إلى الوراء الى التوقعات
on surveillance by George Orwell,
على المراقبة من قبل جورج أورويل،
well it turns out that
يتضح أن
George Orwell was an optimist.
جورج أورويل كان متفائلا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We are right now seeing a much larger scale
نحن نشهد الآن على نطاق أوسع بكثير
of tracking of individual citizens
تتبع للمواطنين الأفراد
than he could have ever imagined.
من كان يمكن أن يتصور أي وقت مضى.
And this here is the infamous
و هذا ما يأتي بالسائنة
NSA data center in Utah.
ولاية الاستخبارات في ولاية يوتا
Due to be opened very soon,
من المقرر أن تفتح قريبا جدا،
it will be both a supercomputing center
سيكون كل من ، مركز الحوسبة الفائقة
and a data storage center.
ومركز تخزين البيانات.
You could basically imagine it has a large hall
هل يمكن أن نتصور في الأساس كان لديه قاعة كبيرة
filled with hard drives storing data
مليئة بمحركات الأقراص الصلبة لتخزين البيانات
they are collecting.
التي يجمعونها
And it's a pretty big building.
انه بناء كبيرة جدا.
How big? Well, I can give you the numbers --
كبير الى اي مدى ؟ حسنا، أستطيع أن أعطيكم أرقام -
140,000 square meters --
140،000 متر مربع -
but that doesn't really tell you very much.
ولكن هذا لا يقول لكم حقا
Maybe it's better to imagine it as a comparison.
يحتمل انه من الافضل ان تتخيلو هي مقاربة
You think about the largest IKEA store
فكر باكبر مركز بيع ل ايكيا
you've ever been in.
كنت فيه من قبل
This is five times larger.
هذا خمسة اضعافه
How many hard drives can you fit in an IKEA store?
كم محرك اقراص يمكنك ان تضع في مركز بيع ايكيا
Right? It's pretty big.
صحيح ؟ انه كبير جدا
We estimate that just the electricity bill
نحن نقدر أن مجرد فاتورة الكهرباء
for running this data center
لتشغيل مركز البيانات هذا
is going to be in the tens of millions of dollars a year.
سيكون عشرات الملايين من الدولارات سنويا
And this kind of wholesale surveillance
وهذا النوع من المراقبة العامة
means that they can collect our data
يعني أنهم يتمكنون من جمع بياناتنا
and keep it basically forever,
و الاحتفاظ بها ببساطة الى الابد
keep it for extended periods of time,
الاحتفاظ بها لفترات مديدة في الحياة
keep it for years, keep it for decades.
لسنين و عقود
And this opens up completely new kinds of risks
و هذا ما يفتح نوع جديد من المخاطر
to us all.
لنا جميعا
And what this is is that it is wholesale
و ماهو هذا للجميع الا
blanket surveillance on everyone.
مراقبة مبطنة لكل شخص
Well, not exactly everyone,
حسنا , ليس بالضبط كل شخص
because the U.S. intelligence only has a legal right
لان من ذكاء الاستخبارات الامريكية فقط لديها الحق
to monitor foreigners.
لمراقبة الاجانب
They can monitor foreigners
يستطيعون مراقبة الاجانب
when foreigners' data connections
عندما تتصل بيانات الاجانب
end up in the United States or pass through the United States.
سواء كانت داخل الولايات ام عبرها
And monitoring foreigners doesn't sound too bad
ورصد الأجانب لا يبدو سيئا للغاية
until you realize
حتى تكتشف
that I'm a foreigner and you're a foreigner.
انني اجنبي و انت ايضا اجنبي
In fact, 96 percent of the planet are foreigners.
في الواقع، 96 في المئة من الكوكب هم من الأجانب.
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Right?
صحيح
So it is wholesale blanket surveillance of all of us,
اذن فهو تعقب جماعي لنا كلنا
all of us who use telecommunications and the Internet.
كل من يستخدم وسائل الاتصال و الانترنت
But don't get me wrong:
لكن لا تفهموني خطأ
There are actually types of surveillance that are okay.
هناك انواع من الرصد و التعقب الجيدة
I love freedom, but even I agree
انا احب الحرية ، لكني احيانا اوافق
that some surveillance is fine.
ان بعض الترصد جيد
If the law enforcement is trying to find a murderer,
اذا فشل القانون في ملاحقة بعض الجانيين
or they're trying to catch a drug lord
او القاء القبض على تاجر مخدرات
or trying to prevent a school shooting,
او كبح اطلاق نار في مدرسة ما
and they have leads and they have suspects,
و لديهم دلالات و لديهم مشتبه بهم
then it's perfectly fine for them to tap the suspect's phone,
بالتالي من الجيد بالنسبة لهم الاستفادة من هاتف المشتبه به،
and to intercept his Internet communications.
واعتراض اتصالاته عبر الإنترنت
I'm not arguing that at all,
انا لا اجادل في هذا على الاطلاق
but that's not what programs like PRISM are about.
لكن هذا ليس كبرنامج بريزم على الاطلاق
They are not about doing surveillance on people
لا يمارس التعقب للناس
that they have reason to suspect of some wrongdoings.
أن لديه السبب للشك في بعض الأخطاء.
They're about doing surveillance on people
انهم على وشك القيام بمراقبة الناس
they know are innocent.
أنهم يعرفون انهم أبرياء.
So the four main arguments
وبالتالي فإن الحجج الرئيسية الأربعة
supporting surveillance like this,
لدعم المراقبة من هذا القبيل،
well, the first of all is that whenever you start
الاول على الاطلاق انه متى ما بداءت
discussing about these revelations,
نقاش حول هذا الكشف
there will be naysayers trying to minimize
سيكون هناك الرافضين محاولة للتقليل من
the importance of these revelations, saying that
أهمية هذه الفضائح، قائلا ان
we knew all this already,
كنا نعرف كل هذا بالفعل،
we knew it was happening, there's nothing new here.
كنا نعلم أنه كان يحدث، لا يوجد شيء جديد هنا.
And that's not true. Don't let anybody tell you
وهذا ليس صحيحا. لا تدع أحدا يقول لكم
that we knew this already, because we did not know this already.
أن كنا نعرف هذا من قبل، لأننا لم نكن نعرف هذا بالفعل.
Our worst fears might have been something like this,
ربما كان أسوأ مخاوفنا شيئا من هذا القبيل
but we didn't know this was happening.
ولكن لم نكن نعرف هذا ما كان يحدث.
Now we know for a fact it's happening.
الآن نحن نعرف عن حقيقة أنه ما يحدث
We didn't know about this. We didn't know about PRISM.
لم نكن نعرف عن هذا. لم نكن نعرف عن بريزم
We didn't know about XKeyscore. We didn't know about Cybertrans.
لم نكن نعرف عن اكس كي سكور لم نكن نعرف عن سايبرتانس
We didn't know about DoubleArrow.
لم نكن نعرف عن دوبل اارو
We did not know about Skywriter --
لم نكن نعلم عن سكاي رايت
all these different programs
كل هذه البرامج المختلفة
run by U.S. intelligence agencies.
التي تديرها الاستخبارات المريكية
But now we do.
لكننا الان نعلم
And we did not know
و لم نكن نعلم
that U.S. intelligence agencies go to extremes
ان الاستخبارات المريكية تتخذ مواقف متطرف
such as infiltrating standardization bodies
مثل التسلل لهيئات التقييس
to sabotage encryption algorithms on purpose.
لتخريب خوارزميات التشفير على اي غرض
And what that means
و ما يعنيه هذا
is that you take something which is secure,
انك تأخذ شي و هو مؤمن
an encryption algorithm which is so secure
و تطبق علي خوارزمية التشفير التي هي آمنة
that if you use that algorithm to encrypt one file,
هذا إذا كنت تستخدم خوارزمية التي التشفير لملف واحد
nobody can decrypt that file.
لا أحد يستطيع فك تشفير هذا الملف.
Even if they take every single computer on the planet just to decrypt that one file,
حتى لو أخذنا كل جهاز كمبيوتر على هذا الكوكب فقط لفك تشفير هذا الملف واحد،
it's going to take millions of years.
هذا سيحتاج ملايين الاعوام
So that's basically perfectly safe, uncrackable.
لذا هذا امن جدا و غير قابل للاختراق
You take something which is that good
ان تاخذ شئ جيدا لهذا الحد
and then you weaken it on purpose,
ثم تضعفه بغرض ما
making all of us less secure as an end result.
يجعلنا في الاخر غير امنين
A real-world equivalent would be that
ومن شأن أي ما يعادل في العالم الحقيقي يكون ذلك
intelligence agencies would force
وكالات الاستخبارات سوف تغرس
some secret pin code into every single house alarm
بعض الرموز السرية في كل جرس انزار بيت
so they could get into every single house
حتى يستطيعوا الوصول لكل بيت على حده
because, you know, bad people might have house alarms,
لانك ، تعلم ، الاشخاص السيئين قد يكون لديهم جرس انزار للابواب
but it will also make all of us
لكن هذا سيجعلنا كلنا
less secure as an end result.
اقل امانا في اخر المطاف
Backdooring encryption algorithms
خوارزميات اتشفير ما خلف الابواب
just boggles the mind.
فقط يحير العقل.
But of course, these intelligence agencies are doing their job.
لكن بالطبع ، وكالات الاستخبار تؤدي في وظيفتها
This is what they have been told to do:
هذا ما كانوا يقولون لنا
do signals intelligence,
عمل اشارات استخبارية
monitor telecommunications,
برصد الاتصالات
monitor Internet traffic.
رصد تحركات الانترنت
That's what they're trying to do,
هذا ما يحاولون القيام به
and since most, a very big part of the Internet traffic today is encrypted,
و نظرا لان معظم ، جزء كبير من الانترنت
they're trying to find ways around the encryption.
يحاولون ان يجدوا طرق حول التشفيرات
One way is to sabotage encryption algorithms,
طريقة واحدة هي بتخريب تشفير الخوارزميات
which is a great example
التي هي مثال عظيم
about how U.S. intelligence agencies
على كيف وكالات الإستخبارات الامريكية
are running loose.
توسع عملها
They are completely out of control,
انهم غير محدودين بالمرة
and they should be brought back under control.
و ينبغي اعادتهم تحت السيطرة
So what do we actually know about the leaks?
حسنا ما الذي نعرفه فعلا عن التسريبات؟
Everything is based on the files
كل شئ مبني على التصنيفات
leaked by Mr. Snowden.
تسربت السيد سنودن
The very first PRISM slides
شرائح البريزم الاولى
from the beginning of June
لبداية يونيو
detail a collection program where the data
تفاصيل برنامج لجمع البيانات حيث
is collected from service providers,
انها تم جمعها من مقدمي الخدمات،
and they actually go and name the service providers
و ذهبوا حقيقة و سموا مقدمي الخدمات
they have access to.
الذين تمكنوا من الوصول اليهم
They even have a specific date
حتى انهم تحصلوا على بيانات محدده
on when the collection of data began
عندما ابتداء جمع البيانات
for each of the service providers.
لكل مقدم خدمات
So for example, they name the collection from Microsoft
ذلك على سبيل المثال، يسمونه جمع من مايكروسوفت
started on September 11, 2007,
ابتداء من سبتمبر 11 ، 2007
for Yahoo on the March 12, 2008,
ل ياهو في مارس 12 ، 2008
and then others: Google, Facebook,
و بعد ذلك اخرون : قوقل ، فيسبوك
Skype, Apple and so on.
سكايب ، ابل و هكذا
And every single one of these companies denies.
و كل واحده من هذه الشركات تنفي
They all say that this simply isn't true,
كلهم يقولون ان هذا ببساطة غير صحيح
that they are not giving backdoor access to their data.
أنها لا تعطي القدرة او القابلة للوصول إلى البيانات الخاصة بهم
Yet we have these files.
حتى الان لدينا هذه الملفات
So is one of the parties lying,
اذن واحد من هذه الاطراف يكذب
or is there some other alternative explanation?
او هناك تفسير اخر
And one explanation would be
و احد هذه التفسيرات سيكون
that these parties, these service providers,
أن هذه الأحزاب، مقدمي هذه الخدمة
are not cooperating.
لا يتعاونون.
Instead, they've been hacked.
بدلا من ذلك، لقد تم اختراقهم.
That would explain it. They aren't cooperating. They've been hacked.
ومن شأن ذلك أن يفسر ذلك. انهم لا يتعاونون. لقد تم اختراقهم.
In this case, they've been hacked by their own government.
في هذه الحالة، لقد تم اختراقهم من قبل حكومتهم.
That might sound outlandish,
قد يبدو هذا غريب،
but we already have cases where this has happened,
ولكن لدينا بالفعل الحالات التي يحدث فيها هذا،
for example, the case of the Flame malware
على سبيل المثال، حالة لهب البرمجيات الخبيثة
which we strongly believe was authored
ونحن نعتقد بقوة انه تمت كتابته
by the U.S. government,
عن طريق الحكومة الامريكية
and which, to spread, subverted the security
و ذلك، لنشر، تخريب أمن
of the Windows Update network,
على شبكة تحديث النوافذ
meaning here, the company was hacked
هذا يعني هنا ان الشركة تم اختراقها
by their own government.
عن طريق حكومتهم
And there's more evidence
وهناك المزيد من الأدلة
supporting this theory as well.
التي تدعم هذه النظرية أيضا.
Der Spiegel, from Germany, leaked more information
دير شبيجل، من ألمانيا، سربت مزيد من المعلومات
about the operations run by the elite hacker units
عن العمليات التي تديرها وحدات النخبة القراصنة
operating inside these intelligence agencies.
عمليات داخل وكالات الاستخبارات هذه
Inside NSA, the unit is called TAO,
داخل وكالة الامن القومي، ويسمى وحدة " تاو "
Tailored Access Operations,
عمليات تصميم الدخول
and inside GCHQ, which is the U.K. equivalent,
وداخل " جي سي اتش كيو "، وهو ما يعادل المملكة المتحدة.،
it's called NAC, Network Analysis Centre.
التي تسمى " ناك " ، مركز تحليل البيانات
And these recent leaks of these three slides
وهذه التسريبات الأخيرة من هذه الشرائح الثلاث
detail an operation
فصلت في عملية
run by this GCHQ intelligence agency
اديرت عن طريق مركز ال جي سي اتش كيو للاستخبارات
from the United Kingdom
من المملكة المتحده
targeting a telecom here in Belgium.
لاستهداف الاتصالات هنا في بلجيكا.
And what this really means
و ما يعنيه هذا
is that an E.U. country's intelligence agency
هو ان وكالات اشتخبارالبلاد
is breaching the security
تقوم باختراق الامن
of a telecom of a fellow E.U. country on purpose,
على الاتصالات للدول التابعة عن قصد
and they discuss it in their slides completely casually,
و تتم مناقشتها في الشرائح الخاصة بعرضهم تماما
business as usual.
العمل كالمعتاد.
Here's the primary target,
وهنا يكمن الهدف الرئيسي،
here's the secondary target,
وهنا يكمن الهدف الثانوي،
here's the teaming.
وهنا كفريق.
They probably have a team building on Thursday evening in a pub.
لديهم على الارجح فريق بناء لمساء يوم الخميس في حانة.
They even use cheesy PowerPoint clip art
حتى انهم يستخدمون البور بوينت كليب ارت
like, you know, "Success,"
كما تعرفون " نجاح "
when they gain access to services like this.
عند الوصول إلى خدمات من هذا القبيل.
What the hell?
ما الذي يحدث ؟
And then there's the argument
و بعد ذلك يحدث الجدل
that okay, yes, this might be going on,
هذا جيد ، نعم ، هذا يمكن ان يحدث
but then again, other countries are doing it as well.
و بعد ذلك ثانية ، دول اخرى تفعلها كذلك
All countries spy.
جميع البلدان تجسس.
And maybe that's true.
و يمكن ان يكون هذا حقيقي
Many countries spy, not all of them, but let's take an example.
العديد من الدول تتجسس ، ليس كلها لكن دعونا ناخذ مثال
Let's take, for example, Sweden.
ناخذ ، على سبيل المثال ، السويد
I'm speaking of Sweden because Sweden
انا اتحدث عن السويد ، لان السويد
has a little bit of a similar law to the United States.
لديها قانون شبيه نسبيا بقانون الولايات المتحدة
When your data traffic goes through Sweden,
عندما تمر بياناتك عبر السويد
their intelligence agency has a legal right by the law
وكالة مخابراتها لديه الحق القانوني
to intercept that traffic.
لاعتراض أن حركة المرور
All right, how many Swedish decisionmakers
اذن ، كم من صناع القرار السويدية
and politicians and business leaders
و السياسيين و رواد الاعمال
use, every day, U.S.-based services,
يستعملون ، كل يوم ، خدمات مقرها الولايات المتحدة
like, you know, run Windows or OSX,
مثل، كما تعلمون، تشغيل ويندوز أو OSX
or use Facebook or LinkedIn,
او يستعملون الفيسبوك او لينكدلن
or store their data in clouds like iCloud
او تخزين بياناتهم في السحب مثل اي- كلاود
or Skydrive or DropBox,
او سكايب درايف او دروب بوكس
or maybe use online services like Amazon web services or sales support?
أو ربما استخدام خدمات الانترنت مثل الأمازون خدمات الشبكة أو دعم المبيعات؟
And the answer is, every single Swedish business leader does that every single day.
والجواب هو، كل واحد سويدي من كبار رجال الاعمال يفعل ذلك كل يوم واحد.
And then we turn it around.
ثم ننتقل حولها.
How many American leaders
كم من قائد امريكي
use Swedish webmails and cloud services?
يستخدم بريد الكتروني سويدي و خدمات سحابية
And the answer is zero.
و الجواب هو صفر
So this is not balanced.
اذا هذا غير متوازن
It's not balanced by any means, not even close.
غير متوازن باي معنى ، ولا حتى بالتقريب
And when we do have the occasional
و حتى عندما نحصل على الفرصة
European success story,
قصة النجاح الاروبي
even those, then, typically end up being sold to the United States.
حتى هؤلاء، تماما تنتهي ببيعها للولايات المتحدة
Like, Skype used to be secure.
كسكايب ، استخدامه للامن
It used to be end-to-end encrypted.
يستعمل ليكون
Then it was sold to the United States.
بعد ذلك بيع للولايات المتحده
Today, it no longer is secure.
الان لم يعد امنا
So once again, we take something which is secure
لذا مرة اخرى ، ناخذ شئ مأمونا
and then we make it less secure on purpose,
و ندعه يفقد الامن بقصد
making all of us less secure as an outcome.
بجعلنا نحن اكثر فقدا للامن تبعا لذلك
And then the argument that the United States
و بعد ذلك المجادلة التي تخوضها الولايات المتحدة
is only fighting terrorists.
هي انها تقاتل الارهاب
It's the war on terror.
هي حرب ضد الارهاب
You shouldn't worry about it.
لا يجب الخوف منها
Well, it's not the war on terror.
فعلا ، هي ليست حرب ضد الارهاب
Yes, part of it is war on terror, and yes,
نعم ، جزء منها كان ضد الارهاب ، و نعم
there are terrorists, and they do kill and maim,
هناك ارهابيين ، و هم بالفعل يقتلون و يطغوا
and we should fight them,
و يجب علينا محاربتهم
but we know through these leaks
لكننا نعلم من خلال هذه التسريبات
that they have used the same techniques
انهم قد استخدموا نفس التكنولوجيا
to listen to phone calls of European leaders,
ليستمعوا الى مكالمات القادة الاروبيين
to tap the email of residents of Mexico and Brazil,
لتعقب البريد الخاص برؤساء المكسيك و البرازيل
to read email traffic inside the United Nations Headquarters and E.U. Parliament,
لقراءة البريد المار من خلال الولايات المتحده مقر ال E.U , و البرلمان
and I don't think they are trying to find terrorists
لا اعتقد انهم يحاولون ايجاد الارهابين
from inside the E.U. Parliament, right?
من داخل البرلمان ، صحيح ؟
It's not the war on terror.
انها ليست الحرب على الارهاب
Part of it might be, and there are terrorists,
جزء منها قد يكون ، و هناك ارهابيين
but are we really thinking about terrorists
لكن هل نحن حقا نفكر في الارهابيين
as such an existential threat
على نحو انهم موجودون
that we are willing to do anything at all to fight them?
و اننا سنفعل اي شي لنحاربهم
Are the Americans ready to throw away the Constituion
هل الامريكان مستعدين لرمي الدستور بعيدا
and throw it in the trash just because there are terrorists?
و القائه في القمامة فقط لان هنالك ارهابيين
And the same thing with the Bill of Rights and all the amendments
و نفس الشئ مع قانون الحقوق و كل القوانين
and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
و الإعلان العالمي لحقوق الإنسان
and the E.U. conventions on human rights and fundamental freedoms
و. الاتفاقيات المتعلقة بحقوق الإنسان والحريات الأساسية
and the press freedom?
و حرية الصحافة
Do we really think terrorism is such an existential threat,
هل حقا نفكر ان الارهابيين كتهديد موجود
we are ready to do anything at all?
نحن مستعدون لفعل اي شئ على الاطلاق
But people are scared about terrorists,
لكن الناس مذعورة من الارهابيين
and then they think that maybe that surveillance is okay
ثم أنهم يعتقدون أن ربما أن المراقبة على جيدة
because they have nothing to hide.
لان ليس لديهم ما يخفوه
Feel free to survey me if that helps.
خذ حريتك لمسح معلوماتي ان كان هذا مفيد
And whoever tells you that they have nothing to hide
و كل من يقول ان ليس لديه ما يخفيه
simply hasn't thought about this long enough.
ببساطة لم يفكر في الامر جيدا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because we have this thing called privacy,
لان لدينا ما يسمى بالخصوصية
and if you really think that you have nothing to hide,
و ان فكرت ان حقا ليس لديك ما تخفيه
please make sure that's the first thing you tell me,
كن متاكدا ان هذا اول ما ستخبرني به
because then I know
لان بعدها ساعرف
that I should not trust you with any secrets,
انني لن أئتمنك على اي شئ
because obviously you can't keep a secret.
لانك ببساطة لا تحفظ سر
But people are brutally honest with the Internet,
ولكن الناس صادقين بوحشية مع شبكة الإنترنت،
and when these leaks started,
و عندما بدات هذه التسريبات
many people were asking me about this.
العديد من الاشخاص كانوا يسالونني عن ذلك
And I have nothing to hide.
وليس لدي أي شيء لاخفيه.
I'm not doing anything bad or anything illegal.
أنا لا أفعل أي شيء سيئ أو أي شيء غير قانوني
Yet, I have nothing that I would in particular
حتى الآن، وليس لدي أي شيء أود على وجه الخصوص
like to share with an intelligence agency,
ارغب في مشاركته مع وكالة الاستخبارات
especially a foreign intelligence agency.
وخصوصا وكالة الاستخبارات الخارجية.
And if we indeed need a Big Brother,
وإذا كنا بحاجة إلى الواقع الأخ الأكبر
I would much rather have a domestic Big Brother
كنت أود أن يكون بدلا من ذلك بكثير وهو الأخ الأكبر المحلي
than a foreign Big Brother.
من الأخ الأكبر الأجنبي
And when the leaks started, the very first thing I tweeted about this
وعندما بدأت التسريبات، أول شيء بدأت بالتغريد عن هذا
was a comment about how,
وكان تعليق حول كيف،
when you've been using search engines,
عندما تم استخدام محركات البحث،
you've been potentially leaking all that to U.S. intelligence.
كان قد تم تسريب كل ما يحتمل إلى الاستخبارات الأمريكية.
And two minutes later, I got a reply
وبعد دقيقتين، وأنا حصلت على الرد
by somebody called Kimberly from the United States
من قبل شخص يدعى كيمبرلي من الولايات المتحدة
challenging me, like, why am I worried about this?
تحدي لي، مثل، لماذا أنا قلق حول هذا الموضوع؟
What am I sending to worry about this? Am I sending naked pictures or something?
ماذا ارسل للقلق حول هذا الموضوع؟ هل إرسل صور عارية أو شيء من هذا؟
And my answer to Kimberly was
وكان جوابي على كيمبرلي
that what I'm sending is none of your business,
أن ما أقوم بإرساله هو ليس من شأنك،
and it should be none of your government's business either.
وينبغي أن يكون لا شيء من أعمال حكومتكم سواء.
Because that's what it's about. It's about privacy.
لأن هذا هو ما يدور حوله الأمر. الخصوصية.
Privacy is nonnegotiable.
الخصوصية هي غير قابلة للتفاوض.
It should be built in to all the systems we use.
يجب أن يبنى علي جميع الأنظمة التي نستخدمها.
(Applause)
تصفيق
And one thing we should all understand
وشيء واحد يجب أن نفهمه كلنا
is that we are brutally honest with search engines.
هو أن كنا صادقين بوحشية مع محركات البحث.
You show me your search history,
تريني تاريخ البحث الخاص بك،
and I'll find something incriminating
وسوف اجد شيئا للتجريم
or something embarrassing there in five minutes.
أو شيء محرج هناك في خمس دقائق.
We are more honest with search engines
نحن أكثر صدقا مع محرك البحث
than we are with our families.
من نحن مع عائلاتنا.
Search engines know more about you
محركات البحث معرفة المزيد عنك
than your family members know about you.
من أفراد عائلتك يعرفون عنك.
And this is all the kind of information we are giving away,
وهذا هو كل نوع من المعلومات التي يتم التخلي،
we are giving away to the United States.
نعطي بعيدا إلى الولايات المتحدة
And surveillance changes history.
والمراقبة تغير التاريخ
We know this through examples of corrupt presidents like Nixon.
نحن نعرف هذا من خلال أمثلة رؤساء الفساد مثل نيكسون.
Imagine if he would have had the kind of surveillance tools that are available today.
تخيل لو كان قد حصل هذا النوع من أدوات المراقبة التي تتوفر اليوم.
And let me actually quote
واسمحوا لي أن أقتبس فعلا
the president of Brazil, Ms. Dilma Rousseff.
رئيس البرازيل، السيدة ديلما روسيف.
She was one of the targets of NSA surveillance.
كانت واحدة من أهداف المراقبة NSA
Her email was read, and she spoke
كان يقرأ بريدها الإلكتروني، وتحدثت
at the United Nations Headquarters, and she said,
في مقر الأمم المتحدة، وقالت:
"If there is no right to privacy,
"إذا لم يكن هناك الحق في الخصوصية،
there can be no true freedom of expression and opinion,
لا يمكن أن تكون هناك حرية حقيقية التعبير والرأي،
and therefore, there can be no effective democracy."
وبالتالي، لا يمكن أن يكون هناك ديمقراطية فعالة
That's what it's about.
هذا ما يدور حوله الأمر.
Privacy is the building block of our democracies.
الخصوصية هو لبنة من ديمقراطياتنا.
And to quote a fellow security researcher, Marcus Ranum,
وعلى حد تعبير الباحث زميل الأمن، ماركوس
he said that the United States is right now treating the Internet
وقال ان الولايات المتحدة تعامل في الوقت الراهن الإنترنت
as it would be treating one of its colonies.
كما ستعامل واحدة من مستعمراتها.
So we are back to the age of colonization,
لذلك نحن عدنا الى عهود الاستعمار،
and we, the foreign users of the Internet,
ونحن، والمستخدمين الأجانب للإنترنت،
we should think about Americans as our masters.
علينا أن نفكر في الأميركيين باعتبارهم سادة لدينا.
So Mr. Snowden, he's been blamed for many things.
حتى السيد سنودن، ألقي باللوم عليه لأشياء كثيرة
Some are blaming him for causing problems
بعض اللوم له عن التسبب في مشاكل
for the U.S. cloud industry and software companies with these revelations --
لصناعة سحابة الولايات المتحدة وشركات البرمجيات مع هذه الفضائح -
and blaming Snowden for causing problems for the U.S. cloud industry
وإلقاء اللوم عن التسبب في مشاكل سنودن لصناعة سحابة الولايات المتحدة
would be the equivalent of blaming Al Gore
سيكون ما يعادل إلقاء اللوم آل غور
for causing global warming.
عن التسبب في ظاهرة الاحتباس الحراري.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, what is there to be done?
لذلك، هناك ما هو الذي ينبغي القيام به؟
Should we worry. No, we shouldn't worry.
ينبغي علينا أن نقلق. لا، لا ينبغي لنا أن تقلق.
We should be angry, because this is wrong,
يجب أن نكون غاضبين، لأن هذا هو الخطأ،
and it's rude, and it should not be done.
وانها وقحا، وأنه لا ينبغي القيام به.
But that's not going to really change the situation.
ولكن هذا لن يغير الوضع حقا.
What's going to change the situation for the rest of the world
ما يحدث لتغيير الوضع لبقية العالم
is to try to steer away
هو محاولة للابتعاد
from systems built in the United States.
من النظم التي بنيت في الولايات المتحدة.
And that's much easier said than done.
وهذا هو أسهل بكثير من القيام به.
How do you do that?
كيف يمكنك أن تفعل ذلك؟
A single country, any single country in Europe
بلد واحد، أي دولة واحدة في أوروبا
cannot replace and build replacements
لا يمكن أن تحل محل وبناء بدائل
for the U.S.-made operating systems and cloud services.
لأنظمة التشغيل الولايات المتحدة قدمت- والخدمات السحابية.
But maybe you don't have to do it alone.
ولكن ربما لم يكن لديك للقيام بذلك وحدها.
Maybe you can do it together with other countries.
ربما يمكنك أن تفعل ذلك جنبا إلى جنب مع البلدان الأخرى.
The solution is open source.
الحل هو المصدر المفتوح.
By building together open, free, secure systems,
من خلال بناء معا مفتوحة وحرة، ونظم آمنة،
we can go around such surveillance,
يمكننا أن يرحل مثل هذه المراقبة،
and then one country doesn't have to solve the problem by itself.
ومن ثم لا يملك بلد واحد لحل المشكلة بنفسها
It only has to solve one little problem.
فقد الوحيد لحل مشكلة صغيرة واحدة.
And to quote a fellow security researcher, Haroon Meer,
وعلى حد تعبير الباحث زميل الأمن، هارون مير،
one country only has to make a small wave,
بلد واحد فقط تجعل موجة صغيرة،
but those small waves together become a tide,
ولكن تلك الموجات الصغيرة تصبح معا المد والجزر،
and the tide will lift all the boats up at the same time,
والمد يرفع كل القوارب لتصل في نفس الوقت،
and the tide we will build
والمد سنبني
with secure, free, open-source systems,
مع آمنة وحرة وأنظمة المصدر المفتوح،
will become the tide that will lift all of us
سيصبح المد التي من شأنها رفع كل واحد منا
up and above the surveillance state.
وحتى فوق الدولة المراقبة.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
( تصفيق )